Lowell Thomas Jr. Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 3. Personal, 1956-2006; 34 folders
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Sr. to Lowell Thomas Jr., February 1975 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from J. Stuart Pritchard, M.D. to Lowell Thomas Jr., May 1975 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from E[lectra] to Lowell Thomas Jr. and "A Ski Fantasy' Article, October 1975 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Sr. to Tay, February 1976 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from E[lectra] to Tay and Lowell Thomas Jr. and the Boston Herald (14 January 1977) (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Lowell Thomas Jr., December 1, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Sr. to Lowell Thomas Jr., February 21, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Sr. to Lowell Thomas Jr., March 15, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence to Lowell Thomas Jr., April 17, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Sr. to Lowell Thomas Jr., June 27, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. buys Talkeetna Air Service, February 18, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Talkeetna is the Jumping-Off Place, March 1981 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Victor, October 1981-November 1981 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence from Walter Cronkite to Lowell Thomas Jr., November 22, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Alaska Flying Magazine, June 1984 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Postcard to Jim Schendel from Lowell Thomas Jr., May 24, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Lake Placid Calendar, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Biog[raphy] A: 1937 Coronation in London, Around South Am[erica] With the Navy, Dartmouth and the Air Corps, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Biog[raphy] B: Basic Training - B13 - Gunter Field; Turner Field, Albany, Georgia, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Biog[raphy] C: Turkey Next, Iran Next, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Biog[raphy] D: After Tibet; Princeton and the Woodrow Wilson School of Public and Int[ernational] Affairs, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Biog[raphy] E: Cinerama - Seven Wonders; Flight to Adventure; High Adventure with LT [Lowell Thomas], August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Biog[raphy] F: North to Our Future; Autobiog[raphy]13, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Biog[raphy] G: Some Close Calls in the Air, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Autobiography 14, 15, no 16, 17, August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Autobiography 18, 19, "My Heart", August 2006 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, and Destination South Pacific with Lowell Thomas, Jr., undated (Box 13, Folder 34)
- 4. Tibet, 1944-1990; 37 folders
  Series contains photographs by Heinrich Harrer, scripts, correspondence, newspaper clippings, reviews, film notes, and a program for an address by His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama for the Nobel Peace Prize.
  - Seven Years in Tibet 1944-1951 Photographs by Heinrich Harrer (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Ford Hicks, National Lecture Bureau, December 1948, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Script for the lecture at Convent of the Sacred Heart, Philadelphia, January 27, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Lowell Thomas, March 7-8, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Bedford Lions Club Presenting "Out of This World" by Lowell Thomas Jr. Program, April 1950 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Wells, Carveth. Geographically Speaking [newsletter] 43, 44 (29 October 1950, 6 November 1950), October 29, 1950, November 6, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Bessac, Frank. "These Tibetans Killed an American...and Get the Lash for It: This Was the Perilous Trek to Tragedy." Life Magazine (13 November 1950): 130-138, 141., November 13, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - New York Times Book Review, November 26, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Script for lecture film, Circa 1950 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Script versions and edits, Circa 1950, 1959, 1964, 1965, 1968, 1972, 1977, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Tay's [Mary Taylor Thomas] Scrap Book [newspaper clippings], February-May 13, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - "This Is San Francisco" with Jim Grady KCBS [radio book review], April 17, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Travel, September 1951 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1954 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1954 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - "Out of This World", June 1954 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Lowell Thomas Film Captures Tibet's Mystery, July 1954 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Out of This World, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Arabian Sun and Flare (February 2, 1955) (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Out of This World' Is Truly Out of It, June 30, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - High Adventure with Lowell Thomas in Tibet Final Script, February 1958 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - William D. McMahon "Behind the Headlines", December 11, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Guggenheim, Hans. "Lost Horizon for Democracy." Saturday Review. (24 October 1959): 38-39., October 24, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Script for lecture - Platform Narration, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Script for lecture - Platform Narration, 1959, 1960, 1968, 1972, 1977, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Henry S. Bradsher, "AP Foreign Advance for Thursday PMS", After June 1960 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Circa 1960-January 21, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Notes on lecture and film, Circa September 20, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Film Notes, 1966, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Tibetan Review, April 1968 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Office of Tibet. News - Tibet XI: 2 (April-September 1976) (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - Schecter, Jerrold. "Journey to the Lost Horizon." Time (September-October 1976) (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: J. Bruce Long, Blaisdell Institute for Advanced Study in World Cultures and Religions, August 30, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - Program for Address by His Holiness the [14th] Dalai Lama and Lowell Thomas, Jr. lecture notes, September 23, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - Nomination of His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama for the Nobel Peace Prize, July 1, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - Thomas, Lowell Jr. "To follow knowledge like a sinking star." Marist Magazine 2.1 (1989-1990): 25-33. (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 14, Folder 37)
- 5. Turkey and Persia, 1948-1949; 3 folders
  Series contains suggestions from Lowell Thomas regarding future plans, “Where Turkey Faces Russia” lecture to the National Geographic Society, and a bulletin of the Near East Society.
  - [Suggestions from Lowell Thomas regarding future plans], Circa 1948 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - "Where Turkey Faces Russia" lecture to the National Geographic Society, January 14, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - Bulletin of the Near East Society, September-October 1949 (Box 14, Folder 40)
- 6. Objects, 1938-1978; 22 boxes
  Series contains several Bell & Howell cameras, other film materials, a Zeiss Ikon Moviscop, a DeJur Grundig Stenorette machine, awards won by Lowell Thomas Jr., Alaska Statutes, memorabilia from his political career, multiple pieces of cloth, clothing from his school and childhood years, and a ceremonial sword.
  - Lawrence-Smith School Senior Athletic Cup 1938 Won by Lowell Thomas, Jr. (Box 15)
  - "Tibet Lecture Scripture" Binder, Circa 1959-1960 (Box 15)
  - Alaska Statutes Title 9 to Title 16, 1962 (Box 15)
  - Alaska Statutes Temporary and Special Acts Legislative Rules, 1962 (Box 15)
  - Lawrence-Smith School New York City Honor Certificate awarded to Lowell Thomas Jr. for Excellence in English, May 27, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from E[lectra] to Tay, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Unknown object comprised of two small metal half spheres, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - A pair of children's shoes, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Baby outfit, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - One part of a cloth diaper, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Parts of a cloth diaper, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Atlas Warner Movie Light, undated (Box 16)
  - Jay Hammond and Lowell Thomas, jr. button, undated (Box 16)
  - I am for Lowell Thomas, Jr. for Congress Republican button, undated (Box 16)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Lt. Governor button, undated (Box 16)
  - White sheet of cloth, undated (Box 17)
  - White sheet of cloth, undated (Box 17)
  - White piece of cloth, undated (Box 17)
  - White piece of cloth, undated (Box 17)
  - Bell & Howell Auto Master in Leather Bag, undated (Box 18)
  - The Allen Group Inc. 18A77-1 Type 58/U For Use with Solderless Connectors Only PPC, undated (Box 18)
  - Bell & Howell 16mm Electric Eye, undated (Box 18)
  - Bell & Howell Auto Master, undated (Box 18)
  - Cine-Kodak Royal Magazine Camera in Bag, undated (Box 18)
  - Ceremonial Sword, undated (Box 19)
  - Bell & Howell Filmo 16mm Viewer, undated (Box 20)
  - Bell & Howell 16mm Film Rewind, undated (Box 20)
  - Cessna Flight Valet Garment Bag, undated (Box 21)
  - "Sonny" Thomas MKK [stein], undated (Box 21)
  - N. Henry Gellert Award for Lowell Thomas Jr., undated (Box 21)
  - JBT Model 31-F Frequency Meter, undated (Box 22)
  - Griswold Film Splicer Jr. Model 8 & 16 mm J990A, undated (Box 22)
  - Astatic JT-30 [Microphone], undated (Box 22)
  - Bell & Howell 16mm Film Rewind, undated (Box 22)
  - Bell & Howell 16mm Filmo Camera, undated (Box 22)
  - Delco 10 Gauge 1 #856, undated (Box 22)
  - White Cord, undated (Box 22)
  - White Cord, undated (Box 22)
  - Black Cord, undated (Box 22)
  - Black Cord, undated (Box 22)
  - Black Cord, undated (Box 22)
  - Sonco 16mm Projection Lens 3 Inch f/2.0 Coated, undated (Box 22)
  - Sonco 16mm Projection Lens 1.5 Inch f/1.6 Coated, undated (Box 22)
  - Radiant R Lamp, undated (Box 22)
  - Small Leather Belt, undated (Box 22)
  - 4 small lightbulbs in bag from Winchester Electronics, Inc., undated (Box 22)
  - Camera Equipment CO. Camera Oil, undated (Box 22)
  - Stewart-Warner Marine Instrument 82108 Ammeter Kit, undated (Box 22)
  - Bell & Howell Pats.Pend., undated (Box 22)
  - Mueller Pat. Clip, undated (Box 22)
  - Metal Crank, undated (Box 22)
  - Bell & Howell Filmotion Viewer Lamp 30 Watt 115 Volt No. 12519, undated (Box 22)
  - Bell & Howell Filmotion Viewer Lamp 30 Watt 115 Volt No. 12519, undated (Box 22)
  - AN6227B29, undated (Box 22)
  - AN901-5C, undated (Box 22)
  - MS28782-29, undated (Box 22)
  - Light, undated (Box 22)
  - Unknown object - piece of metal, undated (Box 22)
  - Unknown object - piece of metal, undated (Box 22)
  - Unknown object - piece of metal, undated (Box 22)
  - Unknown object - piece of leather, undated (Box 22)
  - F.R.T. [Frances Ryan Thomas] Suitcase, undated (Box 23)
  - Green Wool Dartmouth "D" Sweater, undated (Box 24)
  - Maroon Jacket, undated (Box 24)
  - Khaki Army Corps Jumpsuit, undated (Box 24)
  - Green Trunk labelled "Military Clothes", undated (Box 25)
  - Dartmouth 1946 Pennant (Box 26)
  - American Flag, undated (Box 26)
  - White Linen Pants with Red Stripe, undated (Box 26)
  - White Jumpsuit with Red Stripe, undated (Box 26)
  - White Linen Pants, undated (Box 26)
  - Khaki Pants, undated (Box 27)
  - Khaki Pants, undated (Box 27)
  - Khaki Pants, undated (Box 27)
  - Trousers with Knee Pads, undated (Box 27)
  - Military Shirt, undated (Box 27)
  - Dark Military Dress Shirt, undated (Box 28)
  - Military Jacket, undated (Box 28)
  - Military Jacket, undated (Box 28)
  - Dark Military Dress Jacket, undated (Box 29)
  - Military caps, undated (Box 29)
  - Greenfold Band with "C", undated (Box 29)
  - American Flag, undated (Box 30)
  - Zeiss Ikon Moviscop, undated (Box 31)
  - Portable Tape Recorder Nagra Kudelski II-CI, undated (Box 32)
  - Bell & Howell 16mm Camera, undated (Box 33)
  - Weston Maston II Universal Exposure Meter, undated (Box 33)
  - Magnecorder PT6-A, undated (Box 34)
  - Empty Scotch Magnetic Tape Reel, undated (Box 34)
  - RCA 5Y3 GT Electron Tube, undated (Box 34)
  - RCA 6V6 GT Electron Tube, undated (Box 34)
  - 6SK7 GT Electron Tube, undated (Box 34)
  - RCA 5879 Electron Tube, undated (Box 34)
  - RCA 12AU7 Electron Tube, undated (Box 34)
  - Magnecorder PT6-J, undated (Box 35)
  - Red Wing Shoes Container, undated (Box 36)
  - DeJur Grundig Stenorette Magnetic Earphone, undated (Box 36)
  - DeJur Grundig Stenorette Machine, undated (Box 36)
- 7. Photographs and Film Negatives, 1947-1978
  Series has photos of Lowell Thomas Jr., his friends and family. Many of these photos document his hobbies and his passion for traveling.
  - Roll 1, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Roll 2, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Roll 3, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Roll 4, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Roll 5, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Roll 6, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Group (3), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Group 12, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Group 13, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Group 14, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Group 15, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Group 16, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Group 17, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 13)
  - Group 18, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - Group 19, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - Group 20, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Group 21, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - Group 22, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 18)
  - Group 23, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - Group 24, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - Group 25 [Mount Ararat, Turkey], Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 21)
  - Group 26, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 22)
  - Group 27, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 23)
  - Group 30, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 24)
  - Group ^, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 25)
  - Group (^), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 26)
  - Group 072, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 27)
  - Group AA (black), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 28)
  - Group AA (blue), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 29)
  - Group (3), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 30)
  - Group 12, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 31)
  - Group 13, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 32)
  - Group 14, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 33)
  - Group 15, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 34)
  - Group 16, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 35)
  - Group 17, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 36)
  - Group 18, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 37)
  - Group 19, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 38)
  - Group 20, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 39)
  - Group 21, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 40)
  - Group 22, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 41)
  - Group 23, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 42)
  - Group 24, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 43)
  - Group 25, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 44)
  - Group 26, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 45)
  - Group 27, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 46)
  - Group 30, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 47)
  - Group (^), Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 48)
  - Group ^, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 49)
  - Group 072, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 50)
  - Group AA232A, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 51)
  - Group AA, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 52)
  - Unmatched negatives, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 37, Folder 53)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Skiing, 1948 (Box 37, Folder 54)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr., May 22, 1951 (Box 37, Folder 55)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Lowell Thomas Jr., March 5, 1955 (Box 37, Folder 56)
  - Lowell Thomas, Jr. Publicity Photos, Circa 20 February 1957-17 October 1958 (Box 37, Folder 57)
  - Koda Negs - from "Arctic High Adv[enture]", February 12, 1958 (Box 37, Folder 58)
  - Lowell Thomas, Jr., November 2, 1969 (Box 37, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence and photo from Samuel S. Johnson to Lowell Thomas Jr., February 21, 1978 (Box 37, Folder 60)
  - Photos of Lowell Thomas, Jr. and Tay Thomas, October 25, 1983 (Box 37, Folder 61)
  - [Lowell Thomas Sr. holding Tay Thomas' book], undated (Box 37, Folder 62)
  - Photographs from Lodwick School of Aeronautics Lakeland, Florida, undated (Box 37, Folder 63)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr., undated (Box 37, Folder 64)
  - Jay Hammond, Lowell Thomas, Jr., Tay Thomas, and Mrs. Hammond, undated (Box 37, Folder 65)
  - Photo found with Bell & Howell 16mm Camera, undated (Box 37, Folder 66)
  - Photos found inside Green Trunk labelled "Military Clothes", undated (Box 37, Folder 67)
  - Garst Museum L.T. [Lowell Thomas] and Annie Oakley Exhibits Greenville, Ohio, undated (Box 37, Folder 68)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr., undated (Box 37, Folder 69)
  - Exhibit Print Negatives from Carl Henry Mildest of Mild Cigars Box, undated (Box 37, Folder 70)
  - Carl Henry Mildest of Mild Cigars Box, undated (Box 38)
  - Film from Canisters in Carl Henry Mildest of Mild Cigars Box, undated (Box 39)
  - Film from Canisters in Carl Henry Mildest of Mild Cigars Box, undated (Box 40)
- 8. Miscellany, 1952-2014; 9 folders
  Series contains a program for “Out of This World” by Lowell Thomas Jr. Presented by Beford Lions Club, newspaper clippings, autographs, an AOPA Pilot Magazine, and various notes.
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. "Adventure to the Faraway Fijis." Colliers (27 December 1952), December 27, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Merian Cooper Paid Honor in Washington, February 25, 1+65 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Autographs, October 24, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Aviation - AOPA Pilot Magazine, December 2007 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Ganging Up on Lowell Thomas, Jr., May 16, 2014 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Film scene lists and notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Music Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Items found inside Green Trunk labelled "Military Clothes", undated (Box 13, Folder 43)